Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00661
Sophia Smith Collection
- Documenting Lesbian Lives, 2018 March-April; 2018-S-0035; .5 linear feet (1 regular document box); 1,638.4 Gigabytes (95 digital video, audio and text files)
  - Carolyn Dull interviewed by Kyra McClary, 2018 March 14; Dull, Carolyn; McClary, Kyra; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
    In this oral history, Carolyn Dull describes her childhood in Virginia with a bipolar and extremely religious father, strong mother, and three brothers. She details her experiences as a child raised in an extremely religious household and how that has made her wary of and uninterested in religion; her experiences as a musician, growing up with rock n' roll, and as a founding member of the country rock band Whiskey Creek; she also describes her work history as a food service worker who moved up to work as an accountant, business manager, and chief financial officer at various community service boards and other organizations; her fragmented school history, in which she left college after a year and then slowly got her associate's and bachelor's degrees; and how she became mayor of Staunton, Virginia. Dull discusses her early marriage as a result of an unplanned pregnancy, and subsequently meeting her future wife. Halfway through the interview, her wife, Salome Baugher, enters the interview to share her side of the story, and to talk about her experience with religion, specifically the Mennonite faith, and how their relationship, though legal, is not public knowledge because of Salome's family.
    Carolyn Dull (b. 1951) was born in Leesburg, Virginia, and moved to Staunton, Virginia at six months old, where she has lived ever since. She has been interested and involved with music, specifically rock n' roll, for as long as she can remember, and played in multiple bands before founding the country rock band Whiskey Creek in the early 1980s. She grew up with a religious father who was an Independent Baptist preacher, whom she did not get along with. She spent a year at William and Mary before becoming pregnant with her first and only daughter in 1972, and marrying her boyfriend at the time. She worked in food service until getting her AAS in Accounting from Blue Ridge Community College in 1982 and her BS in Management and Organizational Development from Eastern Mennonite University in 1997. She then worked as an accountant, a business manager, and a CFO at various organizations before retiring in 2015. She ran for a city council position in 2006, and then was elected as Vice Mayor of Staunton, Virginia in 2012, and then was elected to Mayor in 2014. She recently was reelected as Mayor for another four years.
    This interview is open for use with following restrictions on access:
    An Access Agreement must be signed by researchers agreeing not to publish any personally identifying information.
    Interview may not be placed online. Please contact us for more information about how to access this resource.
    Dull, Carolyn
  - Judith Frank interviewed by Karolina Ware, 2018 April 8; Frank, Judith; Ware, Karolina; 1 oral histories (audio and transcript)
    In this oral history, Judith Frank describes her childhood and family dynamics, and their transition to Israel in 1976. She talks about her college experiences in Israel, especially in comparison to the typical U.S. college experience, and what it was like to come back to the U.S. for graduate school. In doing so, she also touches upon how her gender and sexuality have been shaped by these life experiences of family and place. The interview focuses on her work as an author that explores issues including sexuality, butchness, politics, and religion, and how these novels were shaped by her own personal experiences. Frank also delves into her passion for teaching, and the important role she believes that education has in the world. In telling her story, she details her experiences of both mental and physical health, and how those have shaped her familial relationships and her relationship to her own body and self. Frank also discusses what it means to be a queer parent, as well as how aging and being an older parent have influenced that.
    Judith Frank (b. 1958) is currently a professor of English and Creative Writing at Amherst College, and writer who tends to explore the interactions between privileged and marginalized identities in her work. She is the author of Crybaby Butch and All I Love and Know, and has been nominated for and won several awards for these literary works that explores topics related to differences in classes, generations, gender presentation, sexualities, political beliefs, and religion. She grew up in the Chicago area before moving to Israel when she was 17, where she went to college before returning to the U.S. to pursue graduate degrees. She now lives in Amherst, MA with her partner and two children.
    This interview is available for research on-site at Smith College Special Collections; it may not be placed online. Please contact us for more information about how to access this resource.
    The narrator has requested that this interview not be made available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
    Frank, Judith
    - Audio interview of Judith Frank
    - Transcript of interview of Judith Frank (Box 1)
  - Roberta "Bobbie" Geary interviewed by Emma "M." Passy, 2018 April 11; Geary, Roberta; Passy, Emma; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
    In this oral history Bobbie Geary shares her story of growing up in Long Island with a religious, working-class family. As the oldest child out of eight, Geary describes how her role of being the eldest daughter affected her gender expression and relationship with the important adults in her life as she grew up. Through the support of the strong women in her life, Geary speaks of how she got involved with her passion in writing and familiarity with lesbians and feminism. After moving to Manhattan, Geary recalls her experiences with therapy and coming to terms with her lesbian identity. This interview explicitly shows the various ways one can use their interests to become political, for Geary recounts her personal role in starting a lesbian press. Geary also recounts the bar scene of the fifties to seventies, which provides insight as to how different lesbian identities (such as the radicalesbians and sex radicals) evolved throughout LGBTQ+ history. In other words, Geary's interview illustrates the ways therapy, lesbian-only spaces, and family dynamics has shaped the way she views and values her lesbianism.
    Roberta "Bobbie" Geary (b. 1940) grew up in an Irish-Catholic household in Long Island, New York, and is the oldest of her seven siblings. Geary has had a passion for reading and writing since she was young, which was fueled by her grandmother's and great-aunts' support. Geary graduated from Hunter College of CUNY with a BA in psychology, and was introduced to publishing in New York City in the 1970s. While Geary has lived in several states as a freelance writer and editor, she currently resides in Easthampton with her partner of thirty years, Sandy. While Geary emphasizes the fact that she does not call herself political, Geary and her partner are founders of the lesbian press, The Graeae Press, and identify as "proud lesbians."
    Geary, Roberta
    - Video interview of Roberta Geary
    - Transcript of interview of Roberta Geary (Box 1)
  - Pat Griffin interviewed by Caroline Eyman, 2018 March 22; Griffin, Pat; Eyman, Caroline; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
    In this oral history, Pat Griffin describes how her 7th grade gym teacher, an Olympic swimmer, transformed her life into that of an athlete. Her passion and devotion to sports are what allowed her to pursue three sports at the University of Maryland: swimming, basketball, and field hockey. In the interview, she describes her years in college as some of her best years because she was the star on all three teams. Simultaneously though, she developed feelings for one of her basketball teammates. The interview focuses on this relationship and the various ones in-between before she met her wife, Kathy. Aside from the relationships with important figures in her life, the interview discusses her professional career at the University of Massachusetts as a professor in Social Justice Education and her personal life in the Pioneer Valley. The end of the interview focuses on her life in the present and the work she does with building common ground between the LGBTQ population and faith-based colleges and universities.
    Pat Griffin was born on January 2, 1946 in Washington, D.C. She grew up in Silver Spring, Maryland with her mother, father, and younger brother. She attended college in her home state at the University of Maryland. She received her B.S. in Physical Education from Maryland. In addition to her academics at the University of Maryland, she was a three-sport athlete on the swim, basketball, and field hockey teams.
    In 1970, Pat Griffin left Maryland to attend the University of Massachusetts Amherst where she received her Master's degree in Sport Studies and her Ph.D. in Social Justice Education. After earning her degrees, she continued her career at the University of Massachusetts Amherst. She was an assistant/associate professor in Teacher Education in Physical Education, an associate professor in Social Justice Education, and also the Women's Swim Coach. She earned the honor of Professor Emerita when she retired from teaching in 2004. In addition to teaching, she is the author of various works, including her book Strong Women Deep Closets that analyzes the discrimination against lesbians in sports. She remains in the Pioneer Valley after her retirement at her home in Belchertown, Massachusetts with her wife Kathy. She continues advocating for LGBTQ athletes as an independent consultant in athletics and physical education.
    This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
    Griffin, Pat
    - Video interview of Pat Griffin
  - Lisa Hohenemser interviewed by Eloise Lindblom, 2018 March 17; Hohenemser, Lisa; Lindblom, Eloise; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
    In this oral history Lisa Hohenemser discusses the trajectory of her life from her childhood to her goals for the future. She talks about realizing she was a lesbian in college, and the struggles of often being unable to be identified as a lesbian. She characterizes herself in several ways as "walking in two worlds", meaning that in many aspects she finds herself part of one group and part of another. Some examples include her status as a child of German immigrant parents and her sexuality and visibility. An important element of this oral history is Lisa's relationship with her children and partner, and her experiences as a lesbian mother. She also discusses her work with AIDS education in the late 1980s and 1990s, when the crisis was at its peak. She ends with her goals for the future as her children are growing up and becoming independent, giving her the time to go back to work, in whatever form that may take.
    Lisa Hohenemser (b. 1964) was born in St. Louis, Missouri, but was raised in Littleton, Massachusetts, interspersed with two years in the Netherlands, 1973-74, and 1978-79. She received her bachelor's degree from Swarthmore College, and later received a Master's in Public Health from the University of Michigan in 1992. She worked in many areas related to public health, such as with youth affected by AIDS, and was at Johns Hopkins University until she decided to take a departure from her work to stay at home with her young children. She has a partner named Mindy, whom she met in 1989, and they have two children together, Isabel, age 18, and Dylan, 15. She has long been involved in community organization and political activism relating to issues such as women's rights, LGBTQ rights, and environmental protection.
    Hohenemser, Lisa
    - Video interview of Lisa Hohenemser
    - Transcript of interview of Lisa Hohenemser (Box 1)
  - Tryna Hope interviewed by Emily Bellanca, 2018 March 29; Hope, Tryna; Bellanca, Emily; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
    Tryna Hope (b. 1943) grew up in Gary, Indiana and Birmingham, Alabama in an Orthodox Jewish household, obtained her Bachelor's degree in Anthropology from University without Walls, and earned her Master's in Social Work from the University of Connecticut. Until beginning her career in social work, her employment history began in her 30s with erasing stray pencil marks from tests and included record producer for Linda Shear's A Lesbian Portrait (Lesbian Music For Lesbians Only), tax consultant, paralegal, group home Advisor, and assistant manager from a woman's group home. She has also written for small women's print publications. She was involved in the Jane Collective in the early 1970s and co-founded the Northampton chapter of Old Lesbians Organizing for Change in the mid-2010s. In 1974 and 1975, she fought for custody of her daughter in the Hampshire County court, and she was one of the few out lesbian/gay people in the country to eventually obtain child custody.
    In this oral history, Tryna Hope describes her childhood in Birmingham, Alabama as a middle-class, Jewish youth. She briefly talks about her experience with childhood sexual abuse and examines the effects of this abuse throughout her life. The interview focuses on her involvement with activist communities in the South Side of Chicago, Illinois during the late-1960s and early 19070s, her experiences as a lesbian separatist and lesbian mother, and her career as a social worker. At the end of the interview, she also talks about her experiences as an elder and about the shifts she has noted in the lesbian community, primarily regarding the decreased use of the word "lesbian." Hope's story reflects her own journey towards forgiveness/reconciliation with herself and her chosen communities, expands the definition of "coming out" to encompass different aspects of self, and traces her pathway to social work. It also provides insight into tension between separatist and non-separatist lesbians during the 1970s, benefits and limitations of therapy, and some of the intergenerational tensions within the LGBT community (e.g. elder erasure and the loss of "lesbian").
    Hope, Tryna
    - Video interview with Tryna Hope
    - Transcript of interview with Tryna Hope (Box 1)
  - Mary James (pseudonym) interviewed by Jenny Park, 2018 March 23; James, Mary; Park, Jenny; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    This interview is closed at at the request of the narrator until January 1, 2037. The nNarrator is using a pseudonym.
    James, Mary
    - Transcript of interview with Mary James (Box 3)
  - Reba Knickerbocker interviewed by Jessica Keast, 2018 March 31; Knickerbocker, Reba; Keast, Jessica; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Reba Knickerbocker was born in Connecticut in 1966, and, following her parents' divorce, moved with her mother to Oakland, California when she was six. Reba attended Mills College, where she joined the rowing team, and she graduated in 1997 as a nontraditional student. She went on to get her Master's in Exercise and Sports Studies from Smith College in 2003 and has worked various jobs coaching crew since then, the most significant of which was her time as head women's coach at Willamette University. Reba got married in Massachusetts after it was legalized. She lived with her wife in the Pioneer Valley before moving back to California, and lived in Sacramento and the Bay Area before resettling in Salem, Oregon. Following the cut of Willamette's women's crew team and her divorce in 2016, Reba moved back to Northampton and is currently the executive director at Northampton Community Rowing.
    In this oral history Reba Knickerbocker discusses growing up with a lesbian mom and her nontraditional "coming out" in a diverse part of the Bay Area. She describes her relationship with her mother's long-term partner, both her and her mother's lesbian communities, and identifying as butch. Reba also talks about her experiences coaching crew, the lack of racial and economic diversity in rowing, and her attempts to make the teams she's worked with more accessible. She ends the interview by detailing her relationship with her ex-wife, talking about their marriage, moves, and eventual divorce.
    Knickerbocker, Reba
    - Video interview with Reba Knickerbocker
    - Transcript of interview with Reba Knickerbocker (Box 1)
  - CJ Lammers interviewed by Natalie Weiss, 2018 April 2; Lammers, CJ; Weiss, Natalie; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    CJ Lammers (b. 1959) works at The Conway School, helping graduate students create sustainable environmental solutions through a project in the community. She has a BA in Forestry from Southern Illinois University (1981) and a Master's in Urban and Regional Planning with a specialization in Environmental Planning from the University of Virginia (1995). She and her wife Sarah got married four times from 1996 to 2008, when they were de facto plaintiffs in the Prop 8 Supreme Court case. CJ is also the delegate to the State Democratic Convention. She and Sarah live in Chesterfield with their two dogs.
    In this oral history, CJ Lammers (b. 1959) describes her childhood living in a strict, mostly male household in Peoria, IL and Aurora, IL as the fifth of six kids. She talks about her college years working in the dish room as the only woman, working on her degree in Forestry. After college, CJ moved to DC where she stayed for over a decade. Working in the environmental field, from Arborist Inspector to environmental planning, CJ was laid off twice in four years from federal budget cuts. This interview covers her coming out as butch in the early 2000s, and what that identity has meant to her, and what it was like being both closeted and out in the work place. CJ married her wife Sarah four time, the first time in 1996 in a commitment ceremony, and most recently in California, resulting in CJ and Sarah becoming de facto plaintiffs in the Prop 8 Supreme Court case that federally legalized same-sex marriage. The interview ends with her discussion of the local politics in Chesterfield, MA and her dedication to conservation.
    Lammers, CJ
    - Video interview with CJ Lammers
    - Transcript of interview with CJ Lammers (Box 1)
  - Amy Meblin interviewed by Gretta Donckers, 2018 April 1; Meblin, Amy; Donckers, Gretta; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Amy Meblin (b. 1949) grew up on the San Francisco Peninsula, in Menlo Park and Portola Valley, California. She attended Stanford University, the University of Oregon, and the University of California, Santa Cruz, before moving east and completing an independent graduate study in media and writing at Lesley College Graduate School in Cambridge. Meblin's employment history includes a variety of positions in media and communications and environmental education and fundraising, including working as program manager at the Fernald State School for the Massachusetts Executive Office of Health and Human Services. She was also part of the production team of Somerville Community Access Television (SCAT), which released Two in Twenty, a lesbian soap opera. Meblin now resides in Greenfield, Massachusetts where she works at the Franklin Community Co-op and lives happily with her spouse, Alix Carafiol, and their daughter, Syl.
    In this oral history Amy Meblin describes growing up in a left-wing family on the San Francisco Peninsula. She knew from the age of 11 that she was attracted to women but remained closeted until 1972 when she attended Linda Shear's concert at the University of Illinois and encountered lesbian feminist culture. The interview covers her early family life in California and her social and professional life in Massachusetts. Meblin describes Boston's bar scene in the 1970s and also emphasizes the "out" culture in her workplaces, notably at the Fernald School and at her current place of employment, the Franklin Community Co-op. Meblin reflects on the conditions of her life that have allowed for what she experienced as a relative amount of freedom and mobility, both in terms of her material life and her identity, noting a sense of comfort moving between different social worlds. The interview also covers Meblin's current family life, including her marriage to her partner of 33 years, following the legalization of same-sex marriage in Massachusetts in 2008, and her experiences parenting a child that she senses to be queer as well.
    Meblin, Amy
    - Video interview with Amy Meblin
    - Transcript of interview with Amy Meblin (Box 1)
  - Valory Mitchell interviewed by Claire Haug, 2018 March 10; Mitchell, Valory; Haug, Claire; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Valory Mitchell (b. 1946) grew up in southern California, and attended the University of California Berkeley where she received her Ph.D. in Psychology in 1983. Mitchell has worked as a professor at the California School of Psychology, where she served as the coordinator of the Gender Studies emphasis area, director of the Institute for the Psychology of Women, and helped to design a Social Justice track. She has also worked as a psychologist for over 25 years. She is the editor of the collections Lesbian Family Life, Like the Fingers of a Hand and The Long View: Women Doing Therapy in the Last Third of Life, and is the author of numerous publications in journals such as Women in Therapy, Journal of Homosexuality, and the Journal of Lesbian Studies. She has lived in the Bay Area in California since the 1960's.
    In this oral history, Valory Mitchell describes her childhood growing up as the daughter of television writers, her experiences going to the University of California Berkeley in the 1960's and 70's, and her experience of living in the Bay Area for her entire life. The interview focuses on her academic work in the field of psychology, which centers around the psychology of women, LGBT individuals, and aging. The interview also focuses on her relationships with important people in her life including her mother, daughter, and partners, and the impact they have had on her and her lesbian identity. Her story touches on the evolution of the Bay Area LGBT scene from its early days in the 1960's through today.
    Mitchell, Valory
    - Video interview with Valory Mitchell
    - Transcript of interview with Valory Mitchell (Box 1)
  - Patricia Montoya interviewed by Sinai Herrera Vargas, 2018 April 2 and April 9; Montoya, Patricia; Herrera Vargas, Sinai; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Patricia Montoya (b. 1965) grew up in Medellin, Colombia. She was born in a coffee town outside of Medellin, Colombia. The second to youngest of seven children, she was raised by her grandmother, surrounded by aunts, uncles, and cousins. After immigrating to the U.S. in the 80's she became involved in various community projects. Her passion for film began during her involvement in a local news station, DCTV. Currently residing in Northampton, she is a video and film studies visiting professor at Hampshire College, as well as a research associate at the Five College Women's Studies Research Center. She holds an M.F.A. from the University of California, San Diego. She focuses her film projects on queer and U.S./Mexico border identity as well as the immigrant experience, intimacy, and memory through the relationship to urban settings.